This Sunday, holding power. My exclusive
interview with Cuban President Miguel
Diaz-Canel
>> [music]
>> as the island nation faces pressure from
the Trump administration for a change in
leadership. Do you think it is possible
[music] to get a deal with President
Trump? I think dialogue and deals with
the US government are possible but
they're still difficult. Would you be
willing to [music] step down if it meant
saving Cuba? Plus, no deal. The bad news
is that we have not [music] reached the
agreement. Talks between the US and Iran
collapse after 21 hours of high-stakes
negotiations. Where does the conflict go
from here? And allegations [music]
and denials. First Lady Melania Trump
pushing back against claims linking her
to convicted sex offender Jeffrey
Epstein. [music]
I am not Epstein's victim. As she calls
on Congress to hold hearings for Epstein
survivors. And turmoil in the California
governor's race. A former staff member
accuses Congressman Eric Swalwell of
sexual assault.
>> These allegations of sexual assault are
flat false. As top Democrats urge him to
end his gubernatorial campaign. My guest
this morning, Republican Congressman
Byron Donalds [music] of Florida and
Democratic Congresswoman Pramila Jayapal
of Washington State. Joining me for
insight and analysis are Telemundo news
anchor Julio Rivera,
>> [music]
>> Amna Nawaz, co-anchor of PBS NewsHour,
Republican strategist Matt Gorman, and
former Biden White House senior advisor
Steve Ricchetti. Welcome to Sunday. It's
Meet the Press.
From NBC News in Washington, the
longest-running show in television
history, this is Meet the Press with
Kristen Welker.
Good Sunday morning. We are beginning
with a world on edge where the Trump
doctrine of regime change is being
tested. Vice President JD Vance in
Pakistan Saturday for meetings with
Iranian leaders overnight announcing no
deal had been reached to end the war as
the Trump administration works to keep
that ceasefire from collapsing. But
first, a new front in President Donald
Trump's pressure campaign after the fall
of Venezuela's Nicolas Maduro and the
killing of Iran's supreme leader,
President Trump is now warning Cuba
could be next. This week, I traveled to
Havana for the first US television
interview with Cuban President Miguel
Diaz-Canel. It comes as Cuba is locked
in an extraordinary standoff after the
US imposed an oil embargo in January
deepening the country's humanitarian and
economic crisis that the US says started
67 years ago by Cuba's communist
government.
I want to start with President Trump
because President Trump's threats to
take over Cuba come as the United States
has removed President Maduro from power,
has invaded Iran and killed its supreme
leader.
Do you fear you could be killed or
arrested by the United States?
That is very interesting question. Those
of us have who have leadership positions
in the revolution have a strong
commitment to our revolution and to our
heroic people. And in this connection,
our responsibility entails the
conviction and the commitment that we're
willing to give our lives for the
revolution and for the cause that we
defend. So, for me, that is not a matter
of concern.
If the time comes, I don't think there
would be any justification for the
United States
to launch a military aggression against
Cuba or for the US to
undertake a surgical operation or the
kidnapping of a president. If that
happens, there'll be fighting and
there'll be a struggle and we'll defend
ourselves. And if we need to die, we'll
die because as our national anthem says,
dying for the homeland is to live. What
you're saying is very powerful.
But are you afraid for yourself? For
your family? Or are you prepared to, as
you say,
make the ultimate sacrifice
if you are attacked?
I have no fear. I am willing to give my
life for the revolution. Of course,
I would li- I I wouldn't like that to be
the attitude of the US government. Is
Cuba actively bracing for the
possibility of a military attack by the
United States?
Like I've always said in previous
meetings previous interviews
and when I also address the Cuban
people,
it is evident that there are threats out
there. It is part of the rhetoric of the
US government. Cuba has done nothing to
offend the US. Cuba has never said about
attacking the United States or
interfering with the United States
affair affairs. However,
you hear that Cuba is next, that Cuba is
going to be next, that there are there's
a way out, that that they're going to
take over Cuba. So,
from the position of responsibility
within the leadership of the of the
country, that is a warning.
And we need to responsibly protect our
people, protect our project, and protect
our country. So, we are preparing
ourselves for defense. But what is the
concept of our preparation for defense?
We have a doctrine which is entirely
defensive. It is not aggressive. It
doesn't pose a threat. In addition,
we also believe that as we prepare
ourselves to defend is the best way to
avoid war and the best way to preserve
peace. Let's discuss the situation here
in Cuba. The people of Cuba are
suffering right now. Your power grid has
failed. Food and energy are running
dangerously low and these problems
existed in some form before the blockade
was put into effect. Do you take any
responsibility
for the pain Cubans are experiencing?
Usted es el presidente. No se siente
responsable?
The Cuban people is suffering.
And this can be seen in two areas.
In the national
aspect and also at the at the family
level because everything takes place on
a daily basis. But what is the main
cause for that suffering?
Has been the mistakes that I myself have
made or like I said, a collective
leadership or is that suffering or the
government or is that suffering
is the result of the policy of
intensified blockade that the United
States have maintained?
I think that the people can provide that
answer. So, these are a number of
restrictions which are not applied to
any other country in the world.
Therefore,
we lack financing in order to buy food,
to buy supplies for our main productions
and services in order to have the the
medicines that we need and to carry out
the repairs that we need for our
national
energy system and our
industrial
factories. How does that reflect on our
people now? And yet the people of Cuba
say you cannot solely blame the United
States because you can trade with other
countries. The economy has been in
decline for the past 10 years. Hundreds
of thousands of people have left Cuba
over the past decade. Many of them who
are young entrepreneurs. Is that a sign
that the Cuban economy and government
has failed the people of Cuba? La gente
de Cuba?
Like I said,
when you see that at the family level,
how does that happen? There is a
scarcity of
food, scarcity of medicine.
The nights become a very uh
long working nights when you've been 20
hours with a power outage. But this is
before the blockade. People were
suffering before the blockade.
Now, let let me explain. Let me explain.
There's a confusion in terms of the
approach. For example,
we were living under the blockade
conditions but the blockade was
intensified and further tightened and
became qualitatively different in the
second half of 2019 with the
implementation of 240 measures and with
Cuba's inclusion
in the list of countries who supposedly
uh sponsor terrorism. So, everything
became
worsened. So, we have the accumulated
effect of the blockade plus the effect
of the tightening of the blockade and
now
the effect
uh caused by this
energy blockade. And I can say this
responsibly to you, this is not the
fault of the Cuban government. We saw it
with our own eyes. Los vimos con
nuestros ojos. People living in severe
poverty sufriendo in the streets of
Havana, the capital city. Is it time
[clears throat] for Cuba to take some
responsibility?
To look in the mirror and to change its
economic system for the people of Cuba
who are suffering here. Que están
sufriendo.
Nosotros nosotros
siempre hacemos análisis muy
autocrítico. We conduct very
self-critical analysis and assessments
of our reality and we're trying to
constantly transform and change what we
do in order to improve
uh what we do. But that's got nothing to
do with the political system. It is not
our political system that is
embracing that inability to move
forward. Our political system is serving
people. It's serving social justice and
making everyone advance. And it seems
that it bothers other people around the
world because of what it represents,
because it is our system for ourselves,
not that we want to impose our system on
anyone else. And they try to block it
like this. We understand that there are
conversations between Cuba and the
United States. Do you think it is
possible to get a deal with President
Trump?
I think we can have
an approach in terms of what is possible
and what is difficult. I think dialogue
and and deals with the US government are
possible, but they're difficult.
Cuba has always stood by its
commitments, and the United States have
not fulfilled its
part of the deal. In the
At present, the US
The US has been engaged in talks with
other countries, and while these
negotiations are underway, they have
attacked those countries, and all of
this creates a lot of distrust. And we
know that inside the United States there
are forces that whenever they see that
there's a possibility to engage in
discussions, to engage in a dialogue,
they try to undercut and
boycott those talks. Are you talking
directly to Secretary of State Marco
Rubio?
And do you trust him?
We have engaged in talks, and we will be
in talks as long as as the United States
agrees to with the US representative
that they decide
in order to have this relationship with
us.
These
talks are very
complex processes. First, you have to
establish a channel for dialogue. Then,
you need to build an agenda
for the discussions and including both
both
the common interest.
>> Yes.
I haven't spoken to uh Secretary Rubio.
I don't know him. Let's talk about some
of the key demands the United States
has. It includes releasing political
prisoners, scheduling multi-party
elections, and recognizing unions and a
free press. Are you willing to commit to
any of those conditions that the United
States has laid out?
No Nobody has
made those
Nobody has made those demands to us, and
we have
that respect to our political system,
our constitutional order.
Our issues that are not under
negotiations with the United States. And
we need to overcome first then. So, let
me They're giving me the hard wrap. So,
let me let me get these questions out.
There's still more than 1,200 political
prisoners, including one of the most
high-profile political prisoners, Cuban
rapper Maykel Osorbo, who's been
imprisoned since 2021 for writing a
protest song that won two Latin Grammys.
Will you commit to releasing him and the
other political prisoners?
That's another issue in which uh you can
see all of these bias and all these
prejudices. They speak about political
prisoners in Cuba.
Like you said,
where the people is going through a very
difficult situation. There are people in
Cuba who are not in favor of the
revolution.
There are people who do not uh support
the revolution.
And they
uh manifest themselves on a daily basis
against the revolution, and they're not
in prison.
This narrative that has been created,
that image that anyone who speaks
against the revolution is thrown into
jail. That's a big lie. That's a
slander, and that's part of that
construct in order to
uh
s- uh
vilify
and to engage a character assassination
of the Cuban revolution. Would you be
willing to step down if it meant saving
Cuba?
You
are a very important and
recognized journalist. Have you ever
asked that question to any other
president in the world? It's because
it's one of the conditions the United
States is asking for. Would you ever
consider that?
Let me explain. Have you asked that
question to any other president in the
world? Have you asked that question to
any other president in the world?
Could you ask that question to Trump? I
have asked very hard questions of
President Trump.
Is that a question from you, or is that
coming from the State Department of the
US government?
>> is because it's one of the things that
we've heard the US government talk
about, that they want political change
here in Cuba. So, my question is for
you.
If they asked you, if they said, "This
is one condition," would you step
Because of your honesty, I'm going to
assume that you're asking that because
of those reasons.
In Cuba, the people who are
in leadership position
is not elected by the US government, and
they don't have a mandate from the US
government. We have a free sovereign
state, a free state. We have so-
self-determination and independence. And
we are not subjected to the designs of
the uh United States.
On the other hand,
Cuban leaders
are not here representing
an elite of power. You can see my
background, where I was born, my family,
what I've done throughout my life.
We are elected by the people, although
there's a narrative trying to disregard
that. Any one of us
before we become part of a leadership
role, we need to be elected at the
grassroots level in a electoral district
by thousands of Cubans, and then
those who represent the Cubans at the
National Assembly of the People's Power
elect those leadership positions, and
those offices like it happens in many
other countries around the world. So, we
have an election system on the basis of
people's participation. So, whenever we
take these
responsibility position and this
leadership position, it's not out of our
uh personal
ambition or a corporate ambition or or
even a party ambition. We do that
as a mandate by the people, and the
concept of revolutionaries
giving up
has to be done. It's not part of our
vocabulary. If the Cuban people
understand that I am
I'm not fit for office, that I am not
at the I've not risen to the occasion,
then I I should not be holding this uh
position of president.
I will respond to them, but you need to
realize that you should not focus only
on the
uh
president of the country, because we
have a collegiate uh leadership, which
is very closely linked to the people.
But it's not the United States that can
impose anything on us.
And you can watch my full interview with
President Díaz-Canel on
meetthepress.com.
When we come back, Republican
Congressman Byron Donalds joins me next.
Welcome back, and joining me now is
Republican Congressman Byron Donalds of
Florida. Congressman Donalds, welcome
back to Meet the Press.
Good to be back with you. Good morning.
It's wonderful to have you back. We are
of course going to get to Iran in just a
moment, but I want to first get your
reaction to what you heard from the
leader of Cuba. You have called the
Cuban regime a state sponsor of
terrorism that, quote, has to go. You
just heard my conversation. Do you think
that President Díaz-Canel is someone who
the Trump administration can, in fact,
make a deal with, or do you think there
needs to be a wholesale change in
leadership in Cuba?
I believe there needs to be full-scale
regime change in Cuba. What you just
heard was a dictator who wants to have
the same deal
as the Castro brothers, that he wants to
be able to rule Cuba with an iron fist
and die in office. That's what it sounds
That's what it sounded to me. I think
what the American people need to
understand is that Cuba for 67 years has
been a communist dictatorship. They have
suppressed the free speech of the Cuban
people. The Cuban people today are
rationing food. You talked about their
power grid. Their economy's flat on
their back. And I think for what
Díaz-Canel was saying about how there
don't have to be any changes for Cuba to
to be better is a lie. If you examine
the history of governments around the
world, free and open societies like
America, that is where the people
actually thrive and succeed and excel.
In communist dictatorships or theocratic
dictatorships, where you suppress free
speech, you actually don't hold open
elections, you take away property, you
take away property rights, what you find
is that people do not thrive, they do
not excel, they cannot build wealth,
they can't build strong families. In
essence, they can't have the American
dream or that dream in any other any
other part of the world. It starts with
your political system, and when you have
a dictator who wants to remain installed
as opposed to letting the people of Cuba
live free. You heard President
Díaz-Canel say that he is willing to die
for his country. Let me ask you,
Congressman, would you, in fact, support
military action in Cuba if that were the
way to lead to regime change?
I'm not going to stand in in step in
front of what the president and any
decisions that he or Secretary Rubio are
going to make on this front, but I think
it's important for everybody to listen
to his words. He would rather continue
to suppress the people of Cuba to the
point where they have to ration food, to
the point where political opposition is
jailed, where there is no free press, no
ability to communicate, and he believes
that that's that's worth dying for. I
think that says all that needs to be
said.
I want to turn to the other major
foreign policy issue, Iran, of course,
front and center. On Saturday, Vice
President J.D. Vance held talks with the
Iranians in Pakistan, but announced that
no deal had been reached. This morning,
really just moments ago, Congressman,
President Trump posted on social media.
I'll read you part of his post. He says,
quote, "The United States Navy, the
finest in the world, will begin the
process of blockading any and all ships
trying to enter or leave the Strait of
Hormuz." How does blocking the Strait of
Hormuz reopen it, which is what
President Trump has said he wants to see
happen?
Well, first, Kristen, let's establish
something. Our Navy, its creation was
actually to
free international waters from the
Barbary pirates. That's why we have a US
Navy. That's its creation and the
history behind it. The president is
trying to make the next strategic
decision, in my view, which allows for
them to have control over the straits
and establish that control. I think in
the president's comments, he also said
that our men and women would go through
the process of trying to find these
mines that the Iranians dropped into the
Strait of Hormuz and to decommission
those mines and get them out of the way
so that you could have an orderly return
to the Strait of Hormuz being open. Last
thing on this, be very clear, the
Iranians have always been using the
straits as economic terrorism against
the West to protect their theocratic
regime. I mean, we started with Cuba,
now we're on Iran. What is the
consistency here? You have dictatorships
that threaten their people, that
suppress speech, that jail political
prisoners. Obviously, in Iran, we know
there are no respect for human rights or
for or for or for women's rights or for
the rights of people who dissent. They
just killed 40,000 people in the streets
of Tehran this regime. So, the president
is doing what's necessary to accomplish
the main objectives here, and that has
remained to make sure that Iran does not
have a nuclear weapon and to
significantly degrade their ballistic
missiles capabilities. The Iranians
using the Strait of Hormuz against the
rest of the world, the president, I
believe, is doing the right thing trying
to control the straits, possibly in
order to open that up for international
waters so you can have trade move
freely, not just in that region, but for
the rest of the world. Let me drill down
with you on the point that you raised
about potential nuclear weapons.
President Trump said last week that
Iran's stockpile of highly enriched
uranium is, quote, "So far underground,
I don't care about that." From your
perspective, Congressman, does any deal
to end this war have to address Iran's
nuclear program and effectively
dismantle it?
I believe so. I think that's the core
mission that the president has been
talking about for quite some time, and
it's not just over the last 40 days that
we've been dealing with this. The
president has been speaking about this
for years. Number two,
and [clears throat] for the American
people again, please understand what the
president is having to do now is to fix
the foreign policy mess of several
presidents when it's come to Iran. In
his first term as president, through his
sanctions, he had the Iranian government
flat on their back. Joe Biden comes in,
undoes all that. The Iranians were able
to reconstitute their economy and, as a
result, begin the enrichment process
again. So, the president is trying to
take use every lever possible in order
to bring this situation under control
once and for all. A nuclear Iran is just
simply unacceptable because that is a
theocratic regime who is hell-bent on
global jihad. They are hell-bent on
spreading terror around the globe.
That's been their modus operandi for 47
years. Congressman, I want to move to
some domestic issues now. Major headline
this week, the first lady, Melania
Trump, put Jeffrey Epstein back in the
headlines when she made a surprise
announcement denying ties to the
convicted sex offender. You're a member
of the House Oversight Committee, which
was scheduled to hear from former
Attorney General Pam Bondi this coming
Tuesday about her handling of the
Epstein files. The Justice Department
says Bondi's ouster excuses her from
having to appear. Do you think Pam Bondi
should testify this week?
Uh look, I don't actually, at this
point, I don't really think so. Now that
she's a former Attorney General of the
United States,
>> Well, Hillary Clinton, hold on. Hillary
Clinton was in an office and she
testified.
>> Well, let me be let me be very clear.
We're going to be continuing with our
investigations into this matter. The
Oversight Committee has been steadfastly
working on this, also with survivors who
chose to come forward to bring more
information. I think if a former AG
Bondi comes in, that'll be a
determination of the committee as a
whole. Let me also say that the now
former Attorney General, she did come
into the committee in a session to have
open conversation and dialogue with
Republican and Democrat members.
Republican members came Hold on. Let me
explain this. This is important.
Republican members came to that
committee hearing asking the attorney
the former Attorney General Bondi
important questions. The Democrats
refused to answer ask her any questions
because they wanted the cameras on
because they wanted to turn it into a
political circus. And I was in that room
and and disgusted, quite frankly,
because you had members on the Democrat
side of the aisle who had ample ability
to to question former AG Bondi, and they
refused because the cameras weren't on.
>> Congressman, we're almost out of time,
and I have two more questions for you.
You actually voted to hold Bill and
Hillary Clinton in criminal contempt
earlier this year for failing to comply
with a subpoena.
Why shouldn't the same standard apply to
the former Attorney General Pam Bondi?
Well, like I said, we'll see what
happens when we get back to DC. If the
committee still wants the former AG to
come in, then I'm quite sure Pam Bondi
will come in, and you won't even get
down that road. What happened with Bill
and Hillary is that we had a bipartisan
subpoena for them to come in, and the
Clintons basically ignored the subpoena.
So, we had to move through towards
criminal contempt proceedings because
Bill and Hillary were trying to
negotiate their way out of actually
coming in and answering questions. All
right, final question. I want to ask you
about Democratic Congressman Eric
Swalwell of California, who's facing
allegations of sexual assault and
misconduct from former members of his
staff, allegations he denies. One House
Republican has filed a motion to expel
Mr. Swalwell from Congress. On the other
side, Democrats say they're going to
respond with a motion to expel
Republican Congressman Tony Gonzales of
Texas, who's being investigated for
allegations of sexual misconduct. Will
you vote to expel Congressman Swalwell,
and will you vote to expel Congressman
Gonzales?
Um if both comes to the floor, I will be
voting yes on both measures.
These allegations are despicable, and
they demean the integrity of Congress.
These things are just completely
unacceptable as far as I'm concerned.
Both gentlemen need to go home. All
right, Congressman Donalds, thank you so
much for being here on a jam-packed
morning. We really appreciate it.
Thank you. When we come back, Democratic
Congresswoman Pramila Jayapal joins me
next.
Welcome back, and joining me now is
Democratic Congresswoman Pramila Jayapal
of Washington. Congresswoman Jayapal,
welcome back to Meet the Press.
Thank you so much, Kristen. It's great
to be with you. It's great to have you
back. I do want to start on Cuba. You
actually just came back from a five-day
congressional delegation in Cuba, where
you did meet with President Díaz-Canel.
You heard him say in the interview that
he effectively would not commit to the
broad asks of the United States,
including releasing political prisoners,
committing to holding multi-party
elections. Do you think Cuba needs to
take those steps in order to move toward
normalization with the United States?
Kristen, I think what is really
important, and what he said to us, and
what I heard him saying this morning as
well on the interview, is that there
need to be real negotiations. And that
has been a frustration for Cuba, that
there hasn't been a real negotiation
with agenda items on the table for the
United States and for Cuba. And I think
there is a real desire for appropriate
desire for America to respect Cuba's
sovereignty. The embargo is the
longest-running embargo against any
country in world history. The fuel
blockade is just the latest part of
that. But the humanitarian crisis on the
ground and the collective punishment and
cruelty towards the Cuban people,
civilians, by the United States foreign
policy is really outrageous, and I feel
from my visit to Cuba that Americans
would not want that to continue if they
understood what was actually happening
on the ground. And so, that's why we
were there for five days to hear from
all sides. We met with political
dissidents, we met with the president,
as you mentioned, we met with civil
society organizations, religious
leaders, entrepreneurs, people who see
the opportunity for a real normalization
of relations between the United States
and Cuba. Well, and Congressman, I
wonder if you met with the political
prisoners. There are still more than
1,200
of them, and in my conversation with
President Díaz-Canel, he would not
commit to releasing any of them.
You have obviously talked about this.
You just said you met with a number of
people. Do you believe Cuba needs to
release its 1,200 political prisoners in
order for negotiations to move forward
effectively?
I do and this has been something that
I've raised directly with the president
both this time and 2 years ago when I
was in Cuba. I think that was the last
time there were any members of Congress
there. I think I've been the last person
to visit Cuba twice in the last 2 years.
Last time I actually met with the
families of political prisoners. We took
a list in to the president and I think
that what I have heard from the Cuban
government is let's put all these items
on the table. just announce that they
were releasing 2,000 prisoners. Not all
of those are political prisoners, but we
understand that some of them are and I
think that this is the kind of thing
that we should push for in an actual
country-to-country negotiation. Not a
dialogue, but a negotiation with actual
items on the agenda. That's how we're
going to move forward is through that
kind of diplomacy, not through you know
an economic bombing of the
infrastructure of Cuba that hurts just
everyday civilians and inflicts a level
of cruelty onto the Cuban people.
>> Yeah, no, you're right. There's a lot of
skepticism about whether any of those
2,000 were political prisoners at all.
Very quickly, do you believe President
Diaz-Canel is the best person to lead
Cuba or do you agree with the Trump
administration that there needs to be an
overhaul in Cuban leadership?
I don't think it is for the United
States to determine who leads another
country. I don't think we would like
that here in the United States and I
don't think that it's appropriate for us
to dismiss the sovereignty of civilians
in other countries to choose their
leaders. And so I think the way we get
to a true democratic future for Cuba
with dignity and freedom is by those
negotiations and ultimately by the
ability for the Cuban people to thrive
and for
freedom to to reign across Cuba. That's
not through blockading a drop of oil
from reaching an island through bombing
the economic infrastructure of the
island and through maximalist foreign
policy pressures threatening military
intervention. It's through negotiation
and diplomacy. That's how we get there.
Congresswoman, let's talk about Iran
now. As you know, Vice President JD
Vance announcing no deal after marathon
talks with Iran in Pakistan. Do you
support these negotiations as a way to
bring an end to this war? Do you think
that is the best way to bring an end to
it?
I do, Kristen. Absolutely support
negotiations.
Let's remember that
it was Donald Trump who took us out of a
negotiated nuclear arms deal with Iran
that was negotiated by President Obama
in 2015. Donald Trump removed us from
that in 2018 and that is what has led us
to the place that we're in. Those
negotiations took over 2 years. I don't
think that in this situation that we
were necessarily going to get to an
agreement again with a day of
negotiations. I'm
you know
I I feel good that perhaps there's still
a path for these negotiations, but we
should be clear. Donald Trump got us
into this mess. He went into a war with
Iran that was unauthorized and illegal
and because of that we are in the mess
that we're in now. There was no
strategy, no plan, no authorization. We
We are now spending about 1 to 2 billion
dollars a day on this war with Iran and
it is a huge cost for the American
people with rising energy prices, but
also a lack of focus on the domestic
issues that really drive people's lives.
He's saying we don't have money for
child care. We don't have money for
housing because we're at war with Iran.
That was a war of choice. That is a war
of choice and we should never have been
in this position to start with. This is
an absolute outrage that this is what
the Trump administration has gotten us
into and I don't think it's good for the
people of the United States or for the
civilians in Iran and Lebanon across the
Middle East.
>> I do want to ask you about your
colleague Congressman Eric Swalwell. You
heard me discussing this with
Congressman Donalds. He's facing
allegations of sexual assault from a
former staff member which we should say
Swalwell says are completely false and
politically motivated. Notable though
House Democratic Leader Hakeem Jeffries,
Senator Adam Schiff, Congresswoman Nancy
Pelosi are calling for Swalwell to end
his run for California governor. Do you
think that Swalwell should drop out of
the gubernatorial race?
I absolutely do. This is as you know,
I've been very vocal
on behalf of survivors of the Epstein
scandal
and I think that what we are seeing now
is
an emergence of women across the country
who have been dismissed, told to shut
up, told to move on,
who have been abused by men in powerful
positions. This is not a partisan issue.
This cuts across party line and it is
the depravity of the way that women have
been treated and I'm just inspired by
the courage and the bravery of the women
who came forward. This is clearly a
pattern. I've already called for
Congressman Swalwell to drop out of the
gubernatorial race and I think we have
to hold everybody accountable. Do you
think you just heard Congressman Donald
say he would vote to expel Eric
Swalwell? Will you vote to expel Eric
Swalwell?
And Congressman Gonzales, I would. I've
already said that I think that these
things these
charges and allegations and the pattern
of abuse and in Congressman Gonzales'
case, he actually admitted to the affair
with the or to you know uh
harassment with his staffer. This is
also important for staffers across the
capital to see that their bosses don't
get to do this to them. So I do think
that both of them
need to step down from Congress. Let
these investigations happen.
You know, but I but I think that this is
very important that we believe women and
that we show people across the capital
and across the country that we will not
accept this kind of behavior. Very
quickly before I let you go, former Vice
President Kamala Harris
joined several other Democratic leaders
at the Al Sharpton convention this week.
She was asked a question about whether
she was going to run again in 2028. She
said quote I'm thinking about it. Do you
think former Vice President Kamala
Harris should run for president again in
2028? Is she the strongest person to
represent Democrats?
I think we should have a big contested
primary and everyone that thinks that
they have an opportunity to really
represent and show leadership for this
country as president should run and
should make their case and the people
should look very carefully at every
single candidate, but it should be a
happy, big,
you know, exciting
attempt for us to be able to really see
who has what it takes to lead our party
forward. That's what we need bold
leadership and I'm looking forward to a
primary that demonstrates that from lots
of candidates.
>> All right. Well, it's only 2026, but in
some ways it's right around the corner.
Congresswoman Jayapal, thank you so much
for being here this Sunday. We really
appreciate it.
When we come back, the last Cuban leader
to appear on this program 67 years ago
this month. Our Meet the Press minute is
next.
Welcome back. The last Cuban leader to
appear on this broadcast was Fidel
Castro 67 years ago this month. He had
just seized power in Cuba after
overthrowing US-backed strongman
Fulgencio Batista. Castro was asked a
question that would define his
revolution whether he sided more with
communism or democracy.
I am not communism. I am not agree with
communism.
My acts prove
for the price
in Cuba. There is no doubt for me
between democracy and communism. But
not only democracy as a word
that is why we call our ideals humanism
because we not only want to give
freedoms to the people, but to give they
the way of getting their life to eat, to
live.
Not only theoretical words.
And when we come back, former Vice
President Kamala Harris says she's
thinking about running for president
again.
>> [music]
>> The panel is next.
Welcome back. The panel is here. Anchor
of Noticias Telemundo Julio Vaquero,
Anna Navarro, co-anchor of PBS NewsHour
Steve Forrest, former advisor to
President Biden and Matt Gorman,
Republican strategist and our newest NBC
News contributor. Welcome to all of you.
Matt, congratulations.
Steve, welcome. Great to have you here
on the panel. Thank you all for being
here on a big Sunday. Julio, I want to
start with you and what we heard from
the Cuban president. I was struck by a
couple of things, his defiance and the
fact that he didn't commit to making any
changes to holding multi-party
elections, to releasing political
prisoners, which is one of the top
issues. What were your takeaways?
>> Totally. He was very defiant, but I
wasn't surprised by that to be honest
because that has been the the Cuban
government's position since the
beginning of the Cuban revolution.
What is he going to say? Of course, he's
going to say he's not going anywhere,
but Nicolas Maduro was saying the same
thing and he's now in New York.
So, what I was surprised by is by him
the fact that he said that he's not in
conversations with Secretary Marco Rubio
because we do know for a fact that those
conversations are taking place. It's
been reported that
they've been talking to the Castro
family, specifically Raul Castro's
grandson. So, the fact that Miguel
Diaz-Canel is not in those conversations
gives puts him in a very vulnerable
position.
I've spoken to people who are close to
the Cuban government, people who are
against the Cuban government, people in
the island and they all agree on one
point. Removing Diaz-Canel would only be
a symbolic change, not a real
transformation and and transformation is
really needed because at the end this is
this is a moral issue. In the middle of
everything you have the
Cuban people
on the one side with an American
government putting a lot of pressure
because they decided they want change, a
Cuban government that's been unable to
create a sustainable economy.
And the question is for how long can you
squeeze this population before anything
changes?
>> Yeah, just being there on the ground and
the despair in the eyes of the people
there and you're right because what we
hear from Marco Rubio is a call for
wholesale change. And now let me turn to
you because another point that he makes
was about these negotiations, that
there's a lack of trust because they saw
negotiations with Venezuela, with Iran
and then all of a sudden the bombing
started and here we have Vice President
J.D. Vance saying
we didn't get a deal and effectively
saying there wasn't that trust that was
formed. How do you think Cuba is
watching what's happening in Iran right
now? I mean clearly they're watching
very carefully, right? President
Diaz-Canel made that clear to you and
there are historical parallels. These
are nations with 50, 60, 70-year regimes
that pay very close attention to
history, right? These are both nations
where President Trump left deals that
his predecessor brokered previously and
has been unable to make new deals even
while ramping up pressure on both Iran
and on Cuba. War being launched in Iran
as well. The other parallel is of course
as you mentioned is what the Iranian
foreign minister mentioned to me days
after the war there was started which
was it was a bitter experience talking
to the Americans. Multiple rounds of
talks that led nowhere and then the US
and Israel launched their attacks and
that word mistrust was one we heard from
the Iranian negotiators just after this
last round of talks failed as well. But
to understand Iran and Cuba, I think you
have to understand Venezuela as Julio
mentioned which is the president
believed a limited special forces strike
there to remove Maduro in a matter of
days could be reiterated in other places
and Iran has proven that is not true. We
hear from President Diaz-Canel saying
Cuba is not Iran and it's not Venezuela.
Yeah, absolutely. Let's talk about the
implications of all of this politically,
Matt, because here is Vice President
J.D. Vance leading these talks to try to
bring the war to an end. What are the
potential implications for any political
aspirations he may have beyond being
Vice President in 2028?
>> Sure, I mean you talk to his people.
Yeah, you talk to his people and it's
not a fait accompli that he runs in
2028. It's likely certainly, but it's
not this automatic thing. They what
they've also said and they've said this
since he got elected that the best way
to position himself for 2028 is to do
the job he was elected to well. There
are no shortcuts in that. I thought it
was notable even though they might have
disagreed privately Trump and Vance on
Iran according to reports, it was a vote
of confidence and a sign of trust to
send him over there on behalf of Trump
and the government to handle these
negotiations and I think you contrast
that a little bit with who he could be
running against in 2028, Kamala Harris.
She was she was given a broad portfolio
for a president who didn't exactly trust
her. She couldn't define the portfolio.
She didn't execute on it and it became a
liability. Those Vance folks are very
aware of that comparison.
>> Okay, you take me perfectly to my
question for Steve. Steve, this is what
Vice President Kamala Harris had to say
about potentially running in 2028 this
week.
>> Are you going to run again in '28?
Listen, I might.
I might.
I'm thinking about it.
Steve, historically speaking, can
candidates who've suffered a loss like
she lost in 2024 have a comeback?
The answer is yes and I know she is
seriously thinking about this. I I am
certain that she's looking at it. I
think we can take her at
her word that she hasn't made up her
mind officially or finally yet, but I'm
sure she's taking a look at it and she
should. She'd be a very strong contender
if she decides to run.
I will say this and I I noticed that the
National Action Network that there were
another eight or 10 potential Democratic
presidential candidates who also were
interviewed by Reverend Sharpton. So,
many of them appeared and I think every
one of the potential candidates is
laser-focused really for the next 6
months on
the midterm elections and Democrats
winning back control in the House and
Senate. When we ran in 2019, when
President Biden ran in 2019, there were
24 candidates by June of 2019. So, I
expect a very large field for the
Democratic primary and for the race, but
again, there's
there's a lot of work to be done between
now and the midterms and that's where
the focus is going to be first.
>> Well, Matt, how do you think Republicans
are viewing this answer by the Vice
President in the very crowded field
that's gearing up?
>> Unabashed delight.
I mean we would love nothing more than
to to run again against Kamala Harris
and like and that was also the strategy
among Vance too. If you remember the
debate, he was not running against Tim
Walls on the other podium. He was
running against Kamala Harris. He was
very smart in that. Julio, do you think
that there's an appetite for for this
type of a comeback?
I don't know. It's a hard one. I think
we'll have to wait and see. It's still
too early, 2 years before 2028.
I will say this. I talked to James
Talarico this week and he's been able to
make a lot of noise in Texas. He was
very open about the mistakes that
Democrats made in 2024 and how they took
many voters for granted, specifically
Latino voters, which I asked him about.
And and I mean whoever runs, if it's
Vice President Harris or whoever it is,
they will have a lot of work to do to
regain those voters.
>> I mean the work begins in the midterms,
but Julio's right. That's going to be
the key question.
>> 100% and affordability and the economy
remain the top issue for voters year
after year after year. We know which way
that's trending, but also let's get to
the midterms first.
Steve, Steve, how are Democrats feeling
heading in into the midterms? How
bullish particularly when you have
what's happening with Congressman
Swalwell sort of overshadowing? I do
think that Democrats are very positive
about the potential for winning back the
House and the Senate right now and
obviously there was inflation
data that was presented this week at I
think 3.4%
rise in the cost of living and I think
exactly what you said is going to be the
focus the midterm election. All right,
guys, fantastic conversation. Thank you
so very much. Thank you for a great
panel discussion. That is all for today.
Thank you for watching. We'll be back
next week because if it's Sunday, it's
[music] Meet the Press.
>> [music]
>> We thank you for watching and remember
stay updated on breaking news and top
stories on the NBC News app or [snorts]
watch live on our YouTube channel.